Okay so continuing on with the saga of machine level programming
好了，让我们继续进行机器级编程的征程
When NO.4 of our series of this
进入这个系列的第四部分
And I think that the total will be five so we're almost through
我想这个系列总共会有五部分，所以我们几乎快完成了
and I've always it this is a lot of material for the course
对本课程来说，我一直都认为这是很多内容了
It's essentially a third of the course
基本上占了本课程内容的三分之一
If you think about well no not that much but it's a lot of the course
如果你认为…好吧，内容没有占三分之一那么多。但是对课程来说，很多了
And a part that we consider very central to it
而且我们认为这是本课程非常核心的一部分
So a lot of this involves since we're talking about a particular machine the intel x86-64 machines
由于我们正在谈论一台特定的机器，即 Intel x86-64 机器，所以很多内容涉及到
A lot of its kind of low-level nitty-gritty stuff
那种低级别的基本细节
But part of what we hope you also are understanding some of the general principles involved too
但是部分也涉及到我们希望你理解的通用原则
And you'll find if you move from this machine to another machine
同时如果你从这台机器换到另一台机器，你会发现
sort of learning your first assembly language is your hardest one learning successive ones a lot easier
这就像学习你的第一种汇编语言是你最难的，再学下一门就简单多了
So today we're going to talk about data representations
那么，今天我们将讨论数据表示
So far all the programs we've looked at
到目前为止我们所看过的所有程序
Have been either just manipulating integers or long integers and pointers
都只是操纵整数或长整数和指针
So that's all what we'd call scaler data—data that's not in any aggregated form
这就是我们所说的标量数据，即不是任何聚合形式的数据
Today we'll look at places where data gets collected into you put together multiple data elements
今天我们将看看那些把数据收集起来的情形，即讲多个数据元素放在一起
And then see there's really two ways to do that
然后我们会看到实际上有两种方法可以做到这一点
One is with arrays where you can create many copies
一种是使用数组，通过数据你可以创建许多副本
Or many copies of an identical data type
或者说许多相同数据类型的副本
you can have an array of ints and array of pointers
你可以创建整型数组或指针数组
A second is where you have structs
第二种方法是使用结构
So you create a small collection of values that can be of different data types
所以，你可以创建一个包含不同数据类型的值的小集合
And each one you access by its name or a tag
同时每一个值都可以通过其名称或标签访问
And it turns out those definitions can be recursive
事实上，这些定义可以是递归的
So you can have arrays of structs and structs with arrays and nest it to an arbitrary degree
因此，你可以使用结构数组和包含数组的结构，并将其嵌套到任意程度
And what we'll see is both how it's represented in the machine memory
我们将看到的是它在机器内存中的表现方式
And also then what the code looks like that will manipulate these different data structures
以及操纵这些不同的数据结构的代码是怎么样的
And the main thing to see is
主要要看到的是
that there's no...at the machine code level there is no notion of an array that you'd have at a higher level
在机器代码级是没有数组这一更高级的概念的
只是你将其视为字节的集合
except to think of it as a collection of bytes
that you can are in contiguous part of storage
这些字节的集合是在连续位置上存储的
And same with a struct. It's just allocated as a collection of bytes
结构也是如此，它就是作为字节集合来分配的
And it's the job of the C compiler then to generate the appropriate code to allocate that memory
然后，C 编译器的工作就是生成适当的代码来分配该内存
to get the right value when you refer to some element of a struct or an array
从而当你去引用结构或数组的某个元素时，去获取正确的值
But the good news is this is such a commonplace type of requirement for a programming language
但好消息是，对于一种编程语言来说，这是一种如此常见的要求
that the machine gives you sort of instructions that you'll see now they make perfect sense.
以至于机器为你提供了相关的、你认为完全合理的指令
They're exactly designed for this particular class of applications
它们完全是为这类特殊应用而设计的
So we'll talk about structure...array first and then structures or structs
那么，我们先谈谈结数组然后再讨论结构
And I'll also mention we'll do a little bit I'll give you a glimpse of floating point today too
而且我还会提到我们会讲一点点浮点数，给你一个浮点数的初步感受
Because it's worth knowing how floating point arithmetic is implemented as well on a machine
因为也值得去了解如何在机器上实现浮点运算
So the basic idea of array allocation is fairly straightforward
数组分配的基本思想是相当简单的
If you have n and an array with n elements
如果你有 n 和一个包含 n 个元素的数组
then that's represented by enough bytes in memory, all in one span to hold that much data
然后，这会在内存中用足够的字节去表示，所有的字节都在一段范围内来保存那么多数据
So if the underlying data types, say it's an int or a char is a single byte data type
因此，如果所表示的数据类型是，比如说 int ，或者是单字节类型的字符
So to have a array of 12 chars takes 12 bytes
那么，要创建一个 12  字符的数组需要 12 个字节
And int takes four bytes so to have an array of five ints takes 20 bytes
而整型需要四个字节，因此具有五个整数的数组需要 20 个字节
You get the idea you just multiply the size of the underlying data type by the number of elements
你明白只需将要表示数据类型的大小乘以元素数即可
And that's how big the array has to be in terms of bytes
这就是数组在字节数方面的大小
And we've already seen that in the char is one byte
我们已经看到，一个字符是一个字节
And it is for a double or a long would be eight bytes and so would be a pointer
双精度或长整数则是八个字节，指针也是八个字节
So those are all different amounts of storage
所以这些数据类型都有不同的存储量
And you see in this diagram we use the x
在这张图中，你可以看到我们使用 x
Denotes the starting address of the beginning of this region of memory
来表示该内存区域开头的起始地址
And so we can use address computation to compute offsets by adding numbers to x
因此我们可以使用地址计算，通过给 x 加上一个数字来计算偏移量
To get the address of particular elements of this array
来获取此数组的一个特定元素的地址
And that's exactly what the code does
而这正是机器代码要做的事
Oh so in general then if you imagine array A has some underlying type T
所以一般情况下，如果你想像数组 A 的类型是 T
What the elements of the array are
那么数组的元素是什么
And some number of elements in that array in the declaration L
声明中该数组中的元素数目是L
Then we will That declaration actually does two things
然后我们将该声明实际上做两件事
One is it allocates enough bytes of storage to hold the entire array
第一件事是分配足够的存储字节来保存整个数组
And the second from a programming language's perspective
第二事，从编程语言的角度来看
It is the identifier of the array A can in some ways be treated like a pointer
某种程度上，可以像指针一样对待数组A的标识符
That you can do pointer arithmetic off of it
你可以做它的指针运算
And that's one of the features of C
这是C的其中一个特点
that was fairly unique to see when it was created and is still unique to this day
在它被创建的那时候，是一个相当独特的东西，至今也仍然是独一无二的
This idea of the sort of interchangeability of pointers and arrays, array identifiers
即这种指针和数组某种等价性、数组标识符的想法
So for example I can use an array notation to say val[4] is element four of this array
例如，我可以使用数组表示法来说 val[4] 是此数组的元素四
And it's a five element array so that would just be this final element
它是一个五元素数组，所以这只是最后一个元素
But I can also just refer to val
但我也可以只是引用 val
And its underlying data type is as an int *, it's a pointer to int
它表示的底数据类型是 int *，它是指向整型的指针
And its value would be x. It's just a pointer. A pointer is remember an address
它的值是 x 。它只是一个指针。 指针是用来记住地址的
And it's just the address at the beginning of the array
同时它只是数组开头的地址
And I can do pointer arithmetic on val
我可以对 val  进行指针运算
which as you know in C and this is a little confusing we'll go back and forth
这点正如你所了解的C，会有点令人困惑，我们会反复（讨论到它）
Because in C when you do pointer arithmetic
因为当在C语言里做指针运算时
Like you say you know p++ for a pointer
比如说，你知道对一个指针进行 p++
We just give you an example
我们只是举一个例子
So if you had something like char * p  as a declaration
所以如果你有像 char * p这样的声明
And you said p is equal to some string s
你说 p 等于某些字符串s
And then you say p++
然后你说 p++
So you're incrementing that pointer, in this case you're incrementing it by 1
所以你正在递增指针，在这种情况下你在给它加上1
Because the underlying data type is a char
因为表示的数据类型是字符
But if you said something like int *
但如果你比如说 int *
I'll call it ip and I different pen
我会称它为 ip ，同时我是会用不同的笔
And I said you know ip++
我说过你知道 ip++
Then ip would get ip+ what, does anyone know?
然后 ip 会等于 ip 加上什么，有人知道吗？
4! yes!
4！对的！
So it's a confusion in C. This remembrance is the same as saying ip+=1
所以在C语言里，这是让人困惑的一点。看到这个就让人想到在说 ip+=1 一样
But what you're actually doing is incrementing that the number of the value of p by four
但是你实际上正在做的是将 p 的值加上4
Because you want a pointer when you jump from one place to another
因为当你从一个地方跳到另一个地方时，你想要的是一个指针
You want it to increment by enough bytes to point to the next integer in this case for ip
你希望它即 ip 增加足够的字节以指向下一个整数
And so similarly val+1 denotes this value x+4
因此类似地，val+1 表示值 x+4
Because it's a the address of the next integer in the array
因为它是数组中下一个整数的地址
By the way the one thing different between an array and a pointer is I can't say val++, right?
顺便说一下，数组和指针之间有一点不同，我不能说 val++，不是吗？
I can't change the value of val, it's fixed by the declaration
我无法改变 val 的值，根据声明它是固定的值
whereas a pointer I can increment it, I can change it in various ways
而对于指针，我可以增加它的值，我可以通过各种方式改变它的值
And similarly &val[2] Says give me the address of the second element of the array
类似地，&val[2] 是说给我该数组第二个元素的地址
So that would be at x+8
即 x+8
And this is again one of the fundamental properties of C
这又是C的基本属性之一
that basically in C if you take a pointer
即如果你拿一个指针，基本上在C语言里
That's weird
这很奇怪
This is an "i" not very well written
这是一个写得不太好的 "i"
These are equivalent statements
这些是等同的陈述
Right. they are just two notations for the same thing
对，他们只是对同个东西的两种写法。
So on the upper part it says ip+2 meaning
所以在上半部分它是说 ip+2， 表示的是
actually add 8 to ip
实际上将 ip 加上8
And then dereference that
然后间接引用它
It's the same as finding the second element of a array an imaginary array
它和查找一个想像的数组的第二个元素是相同的
where ip is indicates the beginning of the array
其中 ip 表示数组的开头
So that's a very fundamental principle of C that
所以这是C语言的一个非常基本的原则
Again this whole idea of pointer arithmetic is fairly unique to C
再说一遍，指针运算的整个想法对于C语言来说是相当独特的
Question
有问题请讲。
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Pardon? yes!
抱歉，请再说一遍？是的！
The compiler will happily let you use negative values for array indices
编译器很乐意让你使用负值作为数组下标
And it will give you a potentially undefined value
它会给你一个潜在的未定义值
But there's nothing in C that prevents you from giving out of bounds either
但是C中也没有任何东西会阻止你给出一个越界的数
numbers that are too big for an array or too small for an array
不管这些数，对数组而言是太大还是太小
There's no bounds checking in it
C语言里没有边界检查
Yes
请讲
Yes so the question is becoming what about negative indices
是的，这个问题就变成了下标是负数怎么办
And the answer is very simple
答案很简单
Because in other words in general something like ip+x
因为，换句话说，通常类似 ip+ x 的表达式
Maybe...can you see this?
也许...你们看得见吗？
Should I turn it on?...kind of brighter
需要我开灯吗？......更亮点了
Is really equivalent to ip+4
其实相当于 ip+4
So this is the notation
所以这是符号
And...it's really hard to read, isn't it?
真的很难读，不是吗？
And the right-hand side is the computation
而右边是计算
So in C you write it using...you don't have to give scaling factors for your data types
所以在C中你可以这样来写......你不必为你不同的数据类型提供不同的伸缩因子
Otherwise would drive you out of your mind
否则会让你抓狂的
But you..secretly underneath when the compiler generates the code we'll see examples of this
但是当编译器在私底下生成代码时，我们会看到类似这样的例子
It's scaling everything
它会伸缩一切
So now the question that is being asked is what if x is a negative number
所以现在问的问题是，如果x  是负数，该怎么办？
Well the rule still applies
那么规则仍然适用
It's just that the final result will be less than ip instead of greater than ip
只是最终结果将小于 ip 而不是大于 ip
But it's totally valid
但它完全有效
And there's actually times you will use it in this term I can promise you
在这个学期，你有有真正用它的时候，我可以向你保证
Yes question
有问题请讲
[student spaeking]
[学生说话]
No! you can't write 2+ip
不行！你不能写成 2+ip
Try it. I'm pretty sure you can't do that and with pointer arithmetic
你可以试一下。我很确定你不能拿指针运算来这么做
Try if somebody wants to type in some code and do it.I don't think you can do that
如果有人想敲一些代码来这么做，请尝试下。我不认为你可以这么做
But if you did it would have to figure it out that
但如果你这样做，它（解析器）就必须弄清楚这一点
You know the parser knows the data types of its two arguments
你知道解析器知道它的两个参数的数据类型
So yeah you could probably do it I've never seen this
所以，你可能做到这一点，只是我从来没有见过这个
You could do it but the compiler would know that one of the arguments is a pointer and therefore scale the other
你可以这样做，但编译器会知道其中一个参数是一个指针，因此伸缩另一个参数
What you can't do is add two pointers
你不能做的是两个指针相加
You can take the difference of two pointers
你可以让两个指针相减
This is obscure. I'm not even going to tell you about this
这是让人费解的，我甚至都没有打算告诉你们这点
Look it up in K&R. But you can do arithmetic
你们去翻下 K&R 写的那本书（即C 程序设计语言）吧。但你可以做指针运算
But you can only for addition it can only be one pointer in one and then the other has to be a regular integer value
但是你只能对于指针加法运算，只能是一个是指针，另一个必须是常规的整数
And it will scale it appropriately
编译器会适当地伸缩它
So I believe you can do it
所以我相信你能做到
It's just somebody will smack you on the back of the hand, if you actually write code that way
只是有人会打你的手背，如果你真的那么写代码的话
But not the compiler
但不是编译器（敲你手背）
So in particular you know you can...
特别是你知道你可以......
If you go beyond the bounds of an array of this you'll get whatever is beyond the bounds of that array
如果你越过了这个数组的范围，你将得到任何超出该数组范围的东西
And it might be an invalid or it might not even be a valid address
它可能是无效的，甚至可能不是有效的地址
And you get a segmentation fault but more typically you'll get some whatever it happens to be there
然后你得到了一个段错误，但更典型的情况是，你会得到一些正好就在数组范围外的东西
And that's not so bad when you read it, but you can also potentially write it as we saw before
当你阅读它时，这并不是那么糟糕，但你也可能会那么写，正如我们前面所看到的
And corrupt data that's already in memory
然后就破坏了内存中的已有的数据
So here's again the same statement I was making before that
所以这又是我在此之前做出的同样的声明
Ip...val+i just get scaled. The value computed would be the starting address plus 4 times whatever i is
Ip......val+i 会被伸缩。计算出的值将是起始地址加上4倍的 i，不管i是什么
So let's look at...
那么让我们来看......
So that's sort of...that's all C, everything I said before is just basic C stuff
所以这有点......所有的都是C，我之前说过的所有内容都只是C语言的基本内容
Now let's start looking at the actual machine code involved
现在让我们开始看看真正涉及到的机器代码
And so I made up this example here
所以我在这里编造了这个例子
where I declare a...three arrays, each with five ints
在这个例子里，我声明三个数组，每个数组有五个整数
And I go through what is considered sort of good form when you are building up data
同时我采用了一种在构建数据时被认为是好的编程风格
即不要在程序里到处放洒任意常值
that instead of having arbitrary constants sprinkled through the program
often called magic numbers
这些常值经常被叫作魔数
that you instead use a pound define and you give it some meaningful name and some documentation
而是改为使用 #define 来定义，并给它一些有意义的名称和一些文档说明
Usually at the top of a file or a .h file
通常位于一个文件或 .h 文件的顶部
And then the typedef is a very handy way if you're going to create complex data structures
如果你要创建复杂的数据结构，那么 typedef 是一种非常方便的方法
I highly recommend you sort of break that into typedefs
我强烈建议你把它分解为类型定义
Because the declaration notation in C gets fairly obscure fairly quickly
因为C中的声明符号很快就会变得相当费解
But all this is saying is the data type I'm going to call a zip_dig
但我所说的一切都是说我将称之为 zip_dig 的数据类型
is defined to be five...an array of five ints
定义为由五个整数组成的数组
And now whenever I say zip_dig something
现在每当我说 zip_dig 一些东西
I'm just popping down I'm saying this is an array of five ints
我只是突然说，我说这是一个由五个整数组成的数组
And so I created three of them with the appropriate zip code for the schools represented here
所以我用这里展示的学校的相应邮政编码创建了其中三个
And now I'm just making up for sake of presentation actual addresses for these
而现在我只是出于演示，替它们编造了实际的内存地址
In general you don't have any control over that
一般来说，你（对实际的地址）没有任何控制权
And I made it up so that they all happen to be in contiguous part of memory
我刻意让它们整好处于连续的内存位置上
And again there's no fundamental reason that should be true
同样的，这么做是没有根本性的理由的
So you can never trust what particular address anything is ever going to be allocated at
因此，你永远不能相信什么东西会被分配到特殊的地址
But you are certain that each of these blocks will be a contiguous collection of 20 bytes
但你确定这些块中的每一块都是20个字节的连续集合
So here's some example code then, to say
那么这里有一些示例代码，比如
I want to retrieve for one of these arrays,  I want to retrieve a element whose index is digit
我想取回其中一个数组的一个元素，我想取回一个索引是数字的元素
And this gets turned into the following code
这将变成以下代码
So remember the first argument which will be a pointer now
所以请记住现在第一个参数将成为指针
will be passed in register %rdi
会传给寄存器 %rdi
And the second will be an int, will be passed in register %rsi
第二个参数将是一个整型，将传到寄存器 %rsi 中
And what I want to get out of this is an int
而我想要得到的是一个整型
And so you see that it here's where that scaled addressing
所以你看到这是伸缩寻址的地方
This is exactly what it was designed for and why...
这正是它的设计目标以及
and why they went to the trouble of adding this sort of fancy address modes to x86
为什么他们遇到了将这种奇特的地址模式添加到 x86的 麻烦
Because this is such a common thing
因为这是一件很平常的事情
So remember what this says is take %rdi
所以记住，这里要做的是拿 %rdi
And add to it what you get by multiplying %rsi by four...so you scale that
加上 %rsi 乘以 4 得到的结果，所以这里你进行了伸缩
And of course that's exactly the computation we want to do
当然，这正是我们想要做的计算
If we compare it to...you know this is what we're trying to get computed
如果我们将它们进行比较，你知道这就是我们想要计算得到的
It's exactly this computation here
就是这里的计算
And that gives us an address and then we're reading from that address
它给了我们一个地址，然后我们从那个地址读取值
And we're going to copy it in %eax
我们将它复制到 %eax 中
Remember this is an int, so it will be in the erosion the lower four bytes of register %rax
记住这是一个整型数，所以它会占据寄存器 %rax 的低位四个字节
And that's all the code it takes to implement this particular operation
这就是实现此特定操作所需的所有代码
Yes
有问题请讲
So %rdi is the base address of the array yeah ah %rsi on the right side yeah
学生：所以 %rdi　是数组的基地址? 老师：是  学生：... 那么为什么乘以4，再加上右侧的 %rsi ？
This is a typo, thank you! Thanks for pointing it out, I'll make a note of that
这里打错字了，谢谢你指出它，我会记下来的
Right, so this slide is incorrect and I'll fix that
是的，所以这张幻灯片是不正确的，我会修正它的
So this should be %rdi plus %rsi right thanks
所以这里应该是 %rdi  加上 4倍的 %rsi，对吧？谢谢
Noting that, let me make it
让我记下来
Okay
好了
And so now let's just look at a...another...just some code
所以现在让我们看一下另一段代码
In particular what if I wanted to go through one of these arrays
特别是如果我想遍历其中一个数组
And for every element of the array add one to it, so increment every single element by one
对于数组的每个元素加上一，即将每个元素递增一
Well first of all you can see that we're setting up a loop
首先，你可以看到我们正在建立一个循环
And it uses the jump to middle of business...with...where the initial part is to jump to the task
它使用跳转到业务中间，初始部分将跳转到（给元素加一的）任务
And all the tasking involves...we're increment...we're using %rax for i here
所有的工作都涉及......我们正在增加...我们在这里使用 %rax 来保存 i
And we're incrementing it and comparing it at various places
我们正在增加它的值，并在不同的地方比较它的值
But...um...here's the line of code that does all the real work
但是这里才是做真正工作的一行代码
Again it's taking the ith element which i is in %rax, scaling by 4
同样地，它选取第 i 个元素.，其中 i 存放在%rax 里，进行四倍伸缩
Adding it to the base of the array and that gives us an address
将它加到数组的基地址上，这就给了我们一个地址
And now remember you can have an arithmetic instruction
现在不要忘了你有一个算术指令
where the second operand—the destination—is a memory reference
这个指令的第二个操作数即目的地址是内存引用
And what this actually requires is to first read the original value from the memory
而这个指令实际需要的是首先从内存中读取原始值
Do the addition and then store the result back in memory
进行加法运算，然后将结果放回内存中
So this one instruction is exactly...incre...doing this ++ operation on this stored data in the array
因此，这一条指令恰好是对数组中存储的数据执行自增运算
By the way I should mention the whole idea...pointer arithmetic and C was...
顺便说一句，我应该指出指针运算和C语言的全部想法是......
C was really people who had programmed an assembly code for most of their lives
C语言真的是那些他们生命的绝大部分时间编写汇编代码的人
thinking about how could I make this look like a high-level language
在想：我如何让它看起来像一种高一级的语言
but keep all the flexibility, all the tricks I learned to play at assembly code in a programming language
但又在一种编程语言里保持所有的灵活性，以及我学会的在汇编代码里玩的所有技巧
Because it was designed...it was originally designed to implement an operating system
因为它起初是为了实现一个操作系统而设计的
The UNIX operating system
即UNIX操作系统
And historically operating systems were written directly in assembly code
历史上，操作系统直接用汇编代码写的
And these people Kernighan, Dennis Ritchie and ...
而Kernighan、Dennis Ritchie等这些人
realized that the way to do this is to sort of build point arithmetic into a programming language
意识到做到这的方法是在一种编程语言里加入指针运算
So anyways the reason I'm saying this is
所以无论如何，我讲到这点的原因是
you see a pretty close correspondence here between instructions and machine code
你会在C语言里，看到指令、机器代码和构造之间相当密切的关系
and constructs in a programming...in the C programming language
And that whole ++ operator and += is sort of something you see a variations of in assemblly code
整个 ++ 和 += 运算符你会看作是汇编代码中的一种变体
Okay so that's a sort of single dimension array
好了，这是一维数组
And I'd like to just change things up a little bit by having us look at
我想通过改变一些事情来让我们看一下
what's the real difference is between a...arrays and pointers in a programming language in C
C中编程语言中数组和指针之间的真正区别是什么
And so I have a couple of these examples
我有几个这样的例子
that I'll bring out one by one
我会一个接一个地拿出来
But the idea of this is you see the declaration on the left
但是想法是：你看到左边的声明 （译者注：请对照15年之后的PPT或看https://scs.hosted.panopto.com/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=03308c94-fc20-40d8-8978-1a9b81c344ed上拍到投影仪的课程视频）
There's something called a1 and something called a2
有一个东东叫 A1， 而有一个叫 A2
So call those A sub n
所以称之为 An
And now what I want to know for each of these is
现在，对其中每一个东东，我想知道的是：
1) does it compile? is this a valid statement in C
1) 它能通过编译吗？在C中是合法语句吗？
2) second with this potentially give me a null pointer reference because I'm referencing a pointer
2) 其次，这可能会给我一个空指针引用吗？因为我正在引用一个指针
for which the I haven't actually allocated space for them that pointer is indicating
对这个指针，我没有为它指示的空间分配空间
I haven't initialized the pointer to a valid memory reference
我没有初始化指针指向有效的内存引用
3) and then finally if I were to use the sizeof operator on that particular value with that
3) 最后，如果我在那个特定值上使用 sizeof 运算符
and including for the case where there's a * in front of it
同时包括前面有 * 的情况
And part of this is to understand the difference then between an array and a pointer
（用这个例子的）部分原因是要理解数组和指针之间的区别
And the main reason this...the main factor is an array
而主要原因是......主要因素是一个数组
when you declare an array in C, you're both you're actually allocating space
当你在 C 中声明一个数组时，你既在分配空间
Space is being allocated somewhere for it
正在为它分配某个位置的空间
And you're creating a using...allowable now to use...the array name of in pointer arithmetic
同时，你也正在创建一个允许在指针运算使用的数组名称
Whereas when you just declare it an array a pointer
而当你只是声明一个指针时
All you're allocating is the space for the pointer itself
你所分配的只是指针本身的空间
And not for anything that it's...you're pointing to
而没有给它所指向的任何东西（分配空间）
So...
那么
Just to...you probably figured out that these both compile
你可能已经发现这些都是能通过编译的
Let me get my cheat sheet Andy
拿一下我的备忘单给我，安迪
Well but what would be the size of A[1] here
那么这里的 A1 的大小会是多少？
if I ran the sizeof operator on it
如果我对其使用 sizeof 运算符的话
Let's do the easier one. What's the size of A2? Hmm?
让我们处理一个更简单的。A2 的大小是多少？嗯？
Hmm...8
嗯？8！
Because it's a pointer
因为它是一个指针
What's the size of A1? A1 is an array of 3 ints
A1 的大小是多少？ A1 是有3个整数的数组
12, right?
12，对吧？
Oh and those...those aren't...no, oops
哦，那些不是.....不，哎呀
And now if I said * A[1] or * A[2]
现在，如果我说 *A1 或 者 *A2
Those would both compile
那些都会通过编译
Could either of them possibly give you a null dereference
他们其中任何一个可能会让你一个间接引用空指针吗？
[student speak]
[学生说]
Yeah oh yes the pointer itself is null but that the
是的哦，是的，指针本身不是，但是
I haven't dereferenced it yet it's a null pointer
我没有间接引用它，但它是一个空指针
But I haven't...it's not a bad potentially bad reference
但我还没有...这不是一个糟糕的...可能糟糕的引用
Right it's not a runtime...I won't create a runtime error
对，它不是一个运行时......我不会造成运行时错误，
if I just say A2 in my code, okay?
如果我只是在我的代码中说 A2，是吧？
So you're a step ahead of me basically
所以基本上你领先我一步
So in it you kind of answered the second question though
所以在其中你有点回答了第二个问题
This one could give you a null pointer error
这个可能会给你一个空指针错误
If you try to dereference a pointer that hasn't been initialized
如果你尝试间接引用尚未初始化的指针
It doesn't point to anything
它不指向任何东西
Whereas this one is fine
而这个就没问题
And now what's the size of A1 of *A1?
那么现在*A1的大小是多少？
4. And what about *A2
4。那么 *A2 呢？
4, yeah
4，对的
Because they're both pointers to ints
因为它们都是指向整型数
So one way to think about that is as a picture
考虑这些问题的一种方式是看作图片
A1 is like we've been showing here
A1就像我们一直在这里展示的那样
It's an array of 4 ints
这是一个包含4(3)个整数的数组
And when I declare A1, I'm allocating... also the program is allocating
当我声明 A1 时，程序也正在分配
12 bytes of storage that's able to hold that
12个字节的存储空间来容纳数组
A2 on the other hand is just a pointer which I'll show there
另一方面，A2 只是一个指针，我将在那里展示
So it's 8 bytes long
所有它的大小是8个字节
But it doesn't point to anything
它不指向任何东西
So that's what I meant that if you tried to say *A2
如果你试图说 *A2 时，这就是我想表达的，
you'd potentially have a null pointer reference dereference out there
即你可能有一个空指针间接引用
And so that's why this is 8 and this is 12
这就是为什么这是8，而这是12
So those who are the warm-up ones, so let's make it a little more interesting
这些是热身练习，让我们把练习变得有趣一点吧
These aren't in the slides you'll notice but I'm going to I'll update the slides to include these later
你会注意到这些热身练习不在幻灯片中，但是我后面会更新幻灯片把内容加进来
ur...but I think the point that if you find this confusing
但我认为，关键是如果你发现这令人困惑的话
it's a sign that you really really really need to understand
这表明你真的真的真的需要了解
what a pointer is and what an array is
指针是什么以及数组是什么
and how they're the same and how they're different
还有它们是怎么相同以及怎么不同
Because it's a core part of programming in C that will lead to endless hours of confusion
因为它是C语言编程的核心部分，如果你还没有透彻掌握的话，就会导致无休止的困惑
if you don't really have this wired down pretty strongly
So let me just give you a preview of what's so interesting about this
那么，让我预览一下这有趣的内容
Is...I'm going to give you some numbers
我会给你一些数字
And then we're going to have to explain how those numbers come around
然后我们将不得不解释这些数字是如何产生的
Okay
好了
So let's try and understand what's happening here
所以，让我们试着了解这里发生了什么
And you see that all of these declarations involve some combination of pointer and array
并且你看到所有这些声明都涉及指针和数组的某种组合
And the question is it a pointer to an array is it an array of pointers
问题是它是一个指向数组的指针，它是一个指针数组
And the answer to those will depend on the particular syntax
而那些答案将取决于具体的语法
So of course the first one is one you've already seen before
当然第一个是你以前见过的
And so you know that compiles and it's not null and you can dereference it and it's not null
同时你知道它能通过编译、不是空指针，你可以间接引用它因为它不是空指针
But if you tried to say **A1
但如果你试图说 **A1
That's not valid, it won't even compile
那是非法的，甚至不会通过编译
Because you're trying to here take...the data type of *A and it's an int
因为你在这里试图引用的 *A 的数据类型是 int
And then you're trying to take a dereference of an int
然后你试图间接引用一个整数
So that won't compile and therefore you can't even test it
所以这不会通过编译，因此你甚至无法测试它
Okay, the question is for these other three you can see that
好了，问题是，对于其它三个你可以看到
Somehow one is a...well let's look at the bottom two first
不知何故，其中一个...我们先看看底部两个
So the one on the bottom says that
所以底部的那个是说
And this is part of...and there's actually a really great section in Kernighan Ritchie that I highly encourage you
这是 Kernighan&Ritchie 该书的一部分，实际该书其中有一非常棒的一节，的我非常鼓励你
which is how to read pointers how to read declarations in C
这一章节是关于如何读C语言里的指针和声明
And the basic rule is you start from the inside
而基本规则是从内侧开始
And you work your way outward
然后向外读
So that declaration of of A3 says that
所以那个 A3 的声明是说...
with that parentheses...says A3 is a...
带着括号，表示 A3 是......
What is A3?
A3 是什么？
A3 is a pointer
A3 是一个指针
That two parentheses around it
有一对括号把它包起来
What does it point to?
它指向什么？
It points to an array of three ints
它指向一个由三个整数组成的数组
So we can diagram A3 then
那么我们可以这样画图表示 A3
to be...something like this
画成这样样子
A3 is a pointer like I said read it from the inside out A3 is a pointer
A3 是一个指针，像我说的，从内到外读 A3 是一个指针
And what does it point to? It points to an array of three elements
它指向什么呢？它指向一个由三个元素组成的数组
And what type of elements are they? They are ints
那些元素是什么类型呢？它们是整数
So you're sort of reading outward and picking up pieces from the right and from the left as you do this
因此，当你这样做的时候，你有点向外读，看看右边的部分又看看左边的部分
And so when you know that, this all makes sense
所以当你知道这点时，一切都懂了
that these numbers...the size of A3 itself is eight
即这些数字... A3 本身的大小是8
But since it points to an array of three ints the size of *A3 is 12
但由于它指向包含三个整数的数组，*A3 的大小为12
And then **A3 would indicate this particular element of the array
然后 **A3 表示数组里这个特定的元素
And so its size is four
所以它的大小为四个
So these all compile, but which of them could cause a null pointer dereference? Which of the last two?
所以这些都是能编译的，但是它们中的哪一个可能会导致空指针间接引用呢？最后两个中的哪一个？
Guess! You can flip coins
二选一，你可以丢硬币来决定
Yes
有问题请讲
Well I'm only looking at it. I'm trying to fill in A3 right now
好吧，我只是检查它，我现在试着选 A3
So A3 is fine
那么 A3 没问题
But if I said *A3, could that have a null pointer?
但是，如果我说 *A3， 它可能会是一个空指针吗？
Problem? Yes
会出问题吗？会的
Why? Because when I declare A3 here, all I'm declaring is this particular...
为什么呢，因为当我在这里声明 A3 时，我所声明的都是这个特别的(A3)
I'm only allocating enough storage for that pointer
我仅仅为该指针分配足够的存储空间
I haven' initialized...I haven't allocated the space for an array I haven't initialized A3 to actually point to an array
我还有初始化......我没有为数组分配空间......我没有初始化 A3，让它真正指向一个数组
So it could be a null pointer it could be arbitrary junk
所以它可能是一个空指针，它可能是任意垃圾值
But it...the chances of it actually pointing to an array of three ends is highly unlikely
但它...它真的指向一个包含三个整数的数组的可能性极小
So this would be potentially bad...therefor double stars doubly bad, right?
因此，这可能会有坏结果，因此对于双星（指针的指针），是双重的坏结果，对吧？
Okay so now let's look at A4
好了，现在让我们看看A4 （译者注：这里的声明是int (*A4[3])， 15年之后学期的PPT可能也没有包括讨论 A4 的这部分内容）
So A4...to understand that, you actually have to look at the charts in C
所以搞明白 A4， 实际上你要看C语言中的图表
the precedence chart
优先级的那张图表
which if you're like me your book falls open to that
如果你像我一样，书正翻到那张优先级图表的话
precedence chart, the different operators and what levels they are
（那张图表描述的是）不同的运算符和它们的优先级
And one thing you'll see is that
其中你会看到
A level 1 of precedence—the highest precedence—includes square brackets
优先级为1，即最高的优先级，包括方括号
And level 2 includes star
而第2级包括星号
In other words bracket is a higher precedence than star
换句话说，括号的优先级比星号高
So this particular statement here
所以这里的这个特别声明
The binding is actually like this
结合实际上是这样的
It says that A4 is an array of three elements
这个声明是说 A4 是三个元素的数组
And those elements are pointers and they point to int
这些元素是指针，它们指向整数
So A4 is an array
所以 A4 是一个数组
Can you see this?
你们看得见（投影仪）吗？
But each of those elements is pointing to an int somewhere hopefully
但是这些元素中的每一个都希望能够在指向（内存）某个位置的一个整数
And so let's see if that matches the numbers we got
让我们看看它是否与我们得到的数字对得上
So the size of A4 is 24 because it's 8 times 3
所以 A4 的大小是24，因为是8乘以3
If I were to dereference A4
如果我要间接引用A4
It would just indicate this particular pointer
它只是表示这个特定的指针
Right? A4 is an array of pointers
对吧？A4 是一个指针数组
So when I get an element out of that array what I'll get is a pointer
因此，当我从该数组中获取一个元素时，我会得到一个指针
And so A4 (*A4) is a pointer and so it's also 8
所以 A4 (*A4) 是一个指针，所以它的大小也是8
But if I now do a second dereference
但是，如果我现在再做一次间接引用
Then I'll get an int and it's size is 4
那么我会得到一个整数，它的大小是4
Okay
好了
These all compile
这些都能通过编译
So could I have a...could *A4 then cause problems
那么我会......那么 *A4 会造成问题吗？
As far as a null pointer or bad pointer?
就空指针或坏指针来说？
No that's right
不会！对的
No is the correct answer, no is yes
不会是正确答案，不会是对的
Because you've...A4...this you're...A4 is an array, you've defined an array
因为 A4 是一个数组，你定义了一个数组
And it...arrays get allocated by their declaration as a three element array
作为三元素的数组，根据声明，会被分配空间
On the other hand this could give you a null pointer
另一方面，这(**A4)可能会给你一个空指针
Because I haven't initialized the array to anything
因为我还没有将数组初始化为任何东西
So for example if it were initialized all zeros it would just be three not null pointers in that array
因此，例如，如果它被初始化为全部的零，那么它将是该数组中的三个非空指针
So this is sort of the stuff the nitty gritties of C. Question? Yes!
所以这就是C语言的核心细节。有问题？请讲！
[Student speaking] How does it know that the size 12 like I thought see they don't really know how many things are in an array
[学生提问] 它是如何知道大小是12的？如我所想的那样的话，他们并不知道数组中有多少元素
The compiler...question is how...the compiler
编译器...问题是如何......编译器
That what I'm...I'll answer your question by saying remember the compiler knows a lot
那就是我...我会这样回答你的问题，记得编译器知道很多东西
So that in particularly I've declared this to be an array of three pointers
所以特别是我已经宣布这是一个由三个指针组成的数组
I'm compiling for a machine where pointers are eight bytes
我正在一台指针（大小）是八个字节的机器上编译
And so the compiler knows that sp 24 bytes
因此编译器知道是24字节
In general when you're referencing in C
通常，当你在C中引用时
There's no...you know the machine doesn't have built into it any bounds
你知道机器没有内置任何边界
And doesn't do bounds checking for you
而且不会替你进行越界检查
But that's in the runtime execution
但那是在运行时执行中
But in C if I...
但是在C中，如果我......
when I declare something, it's known...it has to be known at that point when the declaration occurs
当我声明某些东西时，它就被知道了，必须在声明出现时被知道
Question?
问题？
Back there
坐后面的那位同学
[student speaking] So instead of doing three I just need a one...that just...[Professor speaking] empty bracket?
[学生]：那么，不要三个，我只需要一个......[老师]： 空的方括号？
Yeah I think empty bracket is just another name for a pointer
是的，我认为空方括号只是指针的另一个名称
Usually it's just given as argument some restrictions on it
通常它只是作为参数，再加上一些限制
But when you use the empty bracket notation in C
但是当你在C中使用空括号表示法时
it's equivalent to doing a pointer declaration you're not allocating any space for
这相当于做一个指针声明，你没有为其分配任何空间
[student speaking] It by saying one graphically...
[学生提问] .......
对的，在这里，当你声明一个数组时，
Yes, right here, when you declare an array
and you give a number—the size of that array, it really allocates that memories
并且你给出一个数字即数组的大小，它确实分配了那些内存
Question
问题请讲
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Yes oh yes and that's the final one
是的哦是的，说的是最后一个
You'll notice that the numbers for A2 and A4 the same and the reason is the same thing
你会注意到 A2 和 A4 的数字相同，原因是它们是一样的
And that again goes by the precedence rules of C
而这同样是按照C的优先级顺序来的
That A2 first binds this way and then this way
A2首先以这种方式结合，然后这种方式
And so A2 and A4 are synonymous just with last parentheses
所以 A2 和 A4 是同义词，区别只是最外层的括号
Okay so that was a bit of an aside
好了，刚刚是有点题外话
But as you can see, I think this is the kind of thing that will really probe your understanding
但正如你所看到的，我认为这是真正检验你的理解的东西
And now you know as a beginning C programmer
现在你知道了，作为一名入门的C程序员
where you don't have a very good sense the underlying representation of a program
在没有很好理解程序的底层表示时
It's really hard to figure these things out. But now that you know
是很难弄懂这些的。但现在你知道
what it means to compile code and you can actually look at compiled code
编译代码意味着什么，你可以真正去读编译代码了
That will sort of clear up a lot of the what's really going on in a program
这会让你搞清楚在一个程序里到底发生了什么
So let's now generalize from one dimension to two just to make life a little more interesting
因此，现在让我们从一维组推广到二维数组，只是为了让生活更有趣点
And again that's an important principle to understand that
再说一次，理解这的一个重要原则是
in a...when you want to declare a multi-dimensional array and see
在你想要声明一个多维数组的时候，看这里
you do it by a sequence of brackets with the bounds for each one
你可以通过一系列括号、每一个括号给出数组边界来完成
And the reason for that is actually there...
原因其实是......
It it...we'll see that it has to do with this notation that we just went through
我们会看到它和我们刚刚提到的这种说法有关
so if I say int
如果我说 int
it turns out that I can read it like this
事实证明我可以这样读它
that A is an array of three elements
即 A 是一个三元素数组
and each of those elements is in itself an array of five elements of type int
每个元素本身都是一个包含五个整数的数组
And we'll get back to that, but that kind of explains everything I'm about to tell you in this picture
我们会回过头来讨论这个问题，但这样解释了我要在这张照片中告诉你的一切
So in particular if I declare an array with R rows and C columns
所以特别是如果我声明一个包含 R 行、C 列的数组
and you think of it mathematically as sort of a matrix, two-dimensional matrix
在数学里，你可以把它想象成一种矩阵，一个二维矩阵
what it really does is it says we'll see eyes on the
它真正做的是它说我们会看到...
Yeah I'm sorry
抱歉
C actually ends up being the inner element
C 实际上最终是说内侧元素
it says first of all I want Row 0 will be an array of C ints
第0行将是 C 个整数的数组
C being the number of columns
C 是列数
I'll put...so all the elements of row 0 will come first
我会这么放，这样的话第0行的元素在前面
All the elements of row 1 come next and so forth up to the end
接下来是第1行的所有元素，这样直到最后一行
And so the total allocation will be 4 times...the data size times the number of rows times the number of columns bytes
因此总共分配4乘以数据大小乘以行数再乘以列数那么多字节
But the reason why they're in that order
但是元素按照这个顺序排练的原因
which is called row major order
这种顺序称为行优先
Because if we thought of it these terms we go through the first row and then the second row and the third row
因为如果我们想到这种顺序，在遍历这些元素时，我们会到第一行，然后是第二行、第三行
is precisely because of this notation
原因正是因为这种表示法...
Let me write it down like this
让我像这样写下来
Int of A...of well
int A...好吧
Let me just use the the one I said
还是用我刚说的那个
We can write this out as A is a int array
我们可以写出来，A是一个整型数组
A three-element array
包含三个元素的数组
It's over half it's one two three...I'll just put it over here
课程时间超过一半了，现在是两点......我就把它放在这里
Okay so A is a three-element array
好了，所以 A 是一个三元素数组
And or generalizing to this picture A is an array of R elements
并且...或者概括到该图片， A 是包含R个元素的数组
This is the first element, this is the second element and this is the Rth element
这是第一个元素，这是第二个元素，这是第R个元素
But what kind of elements are those
但是那些是什么样的元素
Each is an array of five ints
每个都是包含五个整数的数组
Alright, so within array A here, each subpart of A then
好吧，所以在这里的数组 A 中，那么每个子部分
is an array of C ints
是一个包含C个整数的数组
And so that's why logically the way these are organized
所以这就是为什么逻辑上这些元素这么排列
Actually comes from this declaration notation directly
实际上直接来自这个声明表示法
And we'll see an example of that
我们来看一个例子
So for example if I wanted to
那么，例如，如果我想
extend my zip_dig idea and introduce an array of four of these
扩展我的 zip_dig 想法，来引入一个包含四个这种 zip_dig 元素的数组
I could declare it this way and again with...remember I used a typedef to declare zip_dig
我可以用这种方式声明它，记得我使用了一个 typedef 来声明 zip_dig
But if I were to expand this out
但如果我展开它的话
It was...would be as if I was declaring this array pgh to be a four rows and five columns
看上去就像我声明这个数组 pgh 为一个四行五列的二维数组一样
But what it really is an array of four elements
但它其实是一个四元素的数组
One two three four each of which is an array of five ints
一个两个三个四个，每个元素是五个整数的数组
Okay so think of that nesting
好了，想想那个嵌套
When you read declarations you start from the name of the element
当你读声明时，你从元素的名称开始
And you work your way outward through these brackets and stars in some order
并且你按照某种顺序通过这些括号和星号向外读
And so in particular if I want to reference a particular element of an array
特别是如果我想引用数组的特定元素
The general rule is...wrong here
一般的规则是......这里的PPT写错了
Oh uh the general rule is this one
不，没错，一般规则就是PPT的这个
If I want to reference...literally...oh I'm building up to it
如果我想引用......字面上理解......哦，我正在逐步到一般规则
Uh so yes this shows that A[i]
所以，是的，这里是表示 A[i]
I can actually just do the reference A[i], I don't have to give A[i][j] in C
实际上我可以做引用 A[i]，在C中我不必引用 A[i] [j]
And what that denotes is one of these are rows of the array
而这表示是数组其中的一行
And each of which is an array of C elements of type int
每个都是一个包含C个整数的数组
And so imagine that in general we have k bytes for data type t
因此，想象一下，对于数据类型 t，通常大小是k个字节
The underlying data type in this case of t is an int and k equals four
在这种情况下，t 表示的数据类型是整型，因此 k 等于4
But in general the starting address then of row i
但一般来说，第 i 行的起始地址
would be gotten by multiplying the number of columns by k
可以通过将列数乘以 k 再乘以行号得到
And then multiplying that by the row number
And now if within the array I want to reference an array element A[i][j]
现在如果在数组中我想引用一个数组元素 A[i][j]
Then it comes out to this computation. You take the starting address
那么就有这个计算了。你先取起始地址
You scale the row number by the number of columns
你用行号乘以列数
Add to it which column you want
加上你想要的那一列（的列号）
And then multiply that all by k
然后将加起来的值乘以 k
So the way to see that is here,  I can get to row number i
理解这个的方式就在这里，我可以 i 乘以列数再乘以元素的大小即 4 达到行 i
by just scaling i by the number of columns times the size of the elements are four
And now I want to get to the jth element of this sub array here
现在我想在这里找到这个子数组的第 j 个元素
And I can do that by scaling j by four
我可以通过将 j 乘以 4 来做到
And adding it to the beginning of this sub array
并将其加到此子数组的开头（地址上）
And now I can just collect the force together
而现在我可以一起合并力量（整合公式）
And that's what...and pull it outside here, that's what gives you this formula
把 k 拎出来，这就给了你这个公式
So again the point of this is that
所以，再说一次，这里的重点是
this all kind of is a natural outcome of the declaration
这一切都是声明的自然结果
And it's easy to think of it in terms of this storage model here
这里，根据这里的数组空间是如何分配的存储模型，是很理解它的
of how the actual array is allocated
Okay now a different style of declaration
好了，现在有一种不同的声明风格
is imagine I create three of these arrays
想象一下，我创建了三个这样的数组
And now I want to create an array
现在我想创建一个数组
that contains...that points to these
这个数组指向这些数组
So this is a different data structure you'll observe from before
因此，这是一个你会发现和之前不同的数据结构
What univ now is an array of three pointers
现在的univ是一个由三个指针组成的数组
And each of those pointers points to a one of these arrays of five ints
并且每个指针都指向这些包含五个整数的数组的其中一个
And their underlying data type by the way of these elements are int*, right?
顺便说下，他们表示的数据类型是整数指针，对吧？
And c does not differentiate
同时C不会去分别（元素有多少）
When you want to declare array like this you just say it's an int*
当你想要像这样声明数组时，你只说它是一个整数指针
You don't say how many elements are the underlying array is
你不会说这个数组包含多少个元素
So you'll see by these picture that these are different data structures
你将通过这些图片看到这些是不同的数据结构
So now let's go through the what the assembly code looks like to reference these two data structures
那么现在让我们来看看要引用这两个数据结构的话，对应的汇编代码是长怎么样的
We didn't...do we do the...? I'm sorry uh I would have thought I'd have assembly code
我们没有做（PPT）...我们做了吗？对不起，我以为有汇编代码的
Victor might be a missing slide you
维克多，你可能错过了一张幻灯片
So we'll see...so imagine I wanted to reference...
我们会看看要怎么处理......那么想象一下，我想引用......
I'm sorry I'm confused why there is no
对不起，我有点困惑为什么没有（那张幻灯片）
Ah, there should be...I'm sorry this is...uh...I'm pausing here, because I think...
应该有张的...我很抱歉，我停顿在这里，因为我认为......
I meant to have a slide that would show
我本来是有一张幻灯片来展示代码长什么样的，然而现在我没有
what the code looks like and I don't
Okay well we're going to have to wing it
好吧，我们要临场即兴发挥了
So if you wanted to in assembly code then reference an element of an array,
因此，如果你想要在汇编代码中，引用数组的一个元素，
lLike this multi-dimensional array
比如像这样一个多维数组
what you'll see is that the code kind of builds up a computation like this
你将看到的是汇编代码构建了这样的计算
And typically in the compiled code
通常在编译的代码中
the value of k is a kind of a constant value
k 的值是一种常数
And if it's an array that's been declared with a constant bounds,
如果它是一个已经声明了固定大小的数组，
then the value of C will also be a constant
那么 C 的值也将是一个常数
And so a piece of code for this and that's why it got omitted by accident
所以对应此的一段汇编代码—这就是为什么它被意外省略了—
will basically take this value and use some combination of the memory referencing
将基本上采用此值并使用内存引用、意味和 lea 指令等的某种组合
and shifting and lea instructions and so forth
to implement this computation and then do a dereference
来实现此计算，然后进行间接引用
So let's look at this second example and there is code for this and it's actually a little bit more complex
那么让我们看看第二个例子，这个例子是有汇编代码的，实际上代码有点复杂
Because this is going through two levels of indirection
因为这是通过两个层次的间接（引用）
So you'll see that to get the digit,
所以你会看到，要得到一位（邮编）数字
a particular digit from a particular...one of these of universities, then
一位来自其中某个大学的特定邮编数字
it has to first of all figure out...
它必须首先弄清楚
Do this dereference is get the a pointer to the beginning of the array
做这个间接引用来获得一个指向数组开头的指针
And that's what this reference is doing here
这就是这个引用要做的事
Oh okay but first of all what it's doing is shifting %rsi by two
哦，好吧，但首先它正在做的是左移 %rsi 两位
which is equivalent to scaling the the digit by four
这相当于是将 digit 乘上 4
Because it's getting ready to take that digit of parameter and scale it appropriately
因为它已经准备好接受d igit 这个参数数字并适当地缩放它
And then it takes that number and adds to it
然后它拿这个数字，加上我读数组 univ 得到的值
the value I get by reading from there the array univ
but using...uh...the index scaling it by eight to actually do a memory reference
但是将索引放大8倍来做实际的内存引用
So remember this instruction then—
那么请记住这条指令
and it looks a little weird—-is actually doing a memory reference here
它看起来有点奇怪，实际上在这里做一个内存引用
of this three element array of called univ
引用这个叫做 univ 的三元素数组
So it's reading from memory and doing an array index directly here by scaling
所以它从内存读取，并通过缩放直接在这里计算数组索引
And now getting from that a pointer
然后得到一个指针
adding to that the the scaled value of of the digit
再加上缩放了的 digit
And so that gives me a pointer now as this notation shows
所以这给了我一个指针，如这个记法所示
to the particular element I want and now it does a dereference
指针指向我想要的特定元素，然后现在它做了一个间接引用
So that's a pretty tough example to get as you're one of your first array ones
作为你的第一个数组例子，这是一个非常难的例
And as I said I apologize for missing the reference to a particular element of this array
正如我前面所说的，我为缺失对这个数组的特定元素的引用（的汇编代码）而道歉
is done entirely by computing scaling indices in appropriate ways
（引用是）完全通过以适当的方式计算缩放的下标来完成的
You want to take the array and scale the first index by 20
你想要拿这个数组，将第一个 index 乘上20
Because each row is 20 elements (bytes), it's 5 times 4
因为每行是20个元素（字节），是5乘以4
And you want to scale the digit by 4 to select the particular element within that array
然后你想将 digit 乘上4来选取该数组中的一个特定元素
And so you all this address computation takes place and then there's a single memory reference
因此，所有这些地址计算都（一次性）完成，然后只有单次的内存引用
Whereas in this data structure you have to go through two memory references
而在这个数据结构中，你必须经历两次内存引用
First of all to...you have to index...get the appropriate element here
首先，你必须（根据）索引获取这里相应的元素
But that's just a pointer now
但那现在还只是一个指针
Then we add an offset to that pointer to get the appropriate element in this array here and then we read from that
然后我们向该指针添加一个偏移量以获取此数组中的相应元素，再然后我们从中读取（元素）
So that's what this notation means is that I'm doing two memory references here and just one there
所以这个记法的意思是我在这里做了两次内存引用，而那边的数组只做了一次
And it's a little bit curious because if you look at the C code  it looks the same
这有点让人好奇，因为如果你看看C代码，它看起来是一样的
But the underlying data types are different and so the references are different
但底层的数据类型是不同的，因此引用也不同
Okay so let's look at some other variations on this code
好的，让我们看看这段代码的其它一些变体
And these are all will sort of fall out from these general principles I've described
这些变体都来脱胎自我刚描述的一般原则
So first of all let's introduce an array a two by two
首先让我们引入一个 2x2 数组
I'm sorry sixteen by sixteen array of ints
对不起，是 16x16 的整型数组
And it used to be in C if you wanted to do multi-dimensional arrays
过去在C里面，如果你想要玩多维数组的话
where the size of the array was not fixed at compile time
而这个数组的大小在编译时还没确定下来时
you basically had to implement your own version of that computation I showed before
基本上你必须自己实现一个我前面所展示的一个（地址）计算版本
of scaling the row number by the number of columns and adding to j
即将行数乘以列数，并加上 j
So this is sort of classic C, I've written it as a macro here but you can see it's...
所以这是一种经典的C写法，我在这里把它写成宏，但你可以看到
it's just doing the row major scaling directly here...is address arithmetic
它只是在这里直接进行行优先缩放，是地址运算
Now since a more recent generation of the C compiler
而现在，自从较近的一代即被称为C99的C编译器开始
what they call C99—it was introduced in 1999—
C99 是在1999年引入的，
Um you can actually pass as a parameter an array
你实际上可以作为参数传递一个数组
where the number of elements in the array is also a parameter
其中数组中的元素个数也是一个传递给函数的参数
that's being passed to the the function
And similarly you can declare an array to be of n elements
同样，你可以声明一个包含n个元素的数组
as long as n has been computed before it hit that array declaration
只要在执行那个数组声明之前已经计算了 n 就行
And the compiler will do the right thing it will allocate the proper number of elements
然后编译器就会做该做的事情，即给适当数量的元素分配（适当的空间）
Let's just look at some of this code examples
我们来看一下这些代码例子
And again what we'll see here and...
同样，我们在这里看到......
This will show you an example of the two...the kind of address computation that takes place with a two-dimensional array
这将向你展示一个二维数组的地址计算例子
In this case I know C is 16 and K is 4
在这个例子里，我知道 C 是 16，K 是 4
So if I want to get element i sub j, i j out of this array
因此，如果我想获得数组中 a[i][j] 这个元素
Then first of all I'll scale i by 64
那么，首先我会给 i 乘上 64
Because that's...and I'll add that to the base
因为那是......然后我将把它加到起始地址上
And then I'll scale %rdx by 4 that's j and add it to this array
然后我将 %rdx 即 j 乘上4，并将其加到此数组（前面计算的结果）上
And so...and then do a memory reference there
然后在那里做一个内存引用
So in the end I'm doing...you see these two instructions have done the appropriate
所以最后，你可以看到这两条指令做了恰当的......
The three instructions have done the appropriate scaling of i and j
这三条指令已经完成了对 i 和 j 的适当缩放
added them to the beginning address of a and done the computation
然后将它们加到 a 的起始地址上，计算就完成了
On the other hand if it's a...
另一方面，如果它是...
one...the third example I showed where n is a parameter that's passed to the function.
我展示的第三个例子，其中 n 是一个传递给函数的参数
So it's not known at compile time how big a scaling factor to use
因此在编译时不知道要使用多大的放缩因子
You'll see that it has to use a multiply instruction to do that
你会发现它必须使用乘法指令才能做到这一点
which is a relatively expensive instruction in terms of performance
就性能而言，这是一种开销相对大的指令
Uh...then once it has that that's just n times i
然后一旦它得到了，接下来只是 n 乘以 i
And then it uses various combinations of lea
然后它使用 lea和之前使用的放缩记法的各种组合
and the scaling notation from before
以及之前的缩放符号
to compute an appropriate offset into the array to do the reference
来计算数组的合适偏移量以进行内存引用
So here I could do it with a shift
所以在这个例子里，我可以通过移位指令做到这一点
uh...and here I had to introduce a multiply because I don't know in advance how big it is
而这里我不得不使用一个乘法指令，因为我事先不知道它有多大
If you want to torture yourself
如果你想折磨自己
here's an example I was going to go over of triply nested possibilities and dereferencing of the same idea
这是一个我过去讲的一个例子，这个例子有三重嵌套的可能性和间接引用的相同思路
But let's move on to pointers...uh...just structs
但还是让我们继续到下一个话题指针，哦，不，是结构
So the idea of a struct is actually quite simple
结构的想法实际上非常简单
Uh well the base idea is simple and it gets more complicated
好吧，基本的想法很简单，然后变得更复杂
Uh...the idea of it is I want to...I declare a struct to have some number of fields
它的想法是我想...我声明一个结构有一些成员
each of which can be an int or could be in this case a pointer or could be an array itself
每个都可以是一个 int ，或者在这个例子也下可以是一个指针，还可以是一个数组本身
But the rule is basically what I'll do is allocate enough space
但规则基本上是，我要做的是给结构的每一个字段(field)分配足够的空间
if I introduce one of these structs, for all the different array elements fields in that struct
如果我为struct的所有不同数组元素字段引入其中一个结构
And then I'll basically keep track the compiler will keep track of where each of these fields starts
然后编译器将跟踪每个字段的起始位置
and generate the appropriate code to offset from the beginning
然后生成适当的代码指示（相对结构地址的）字节偏移
So the structure itself, the reference to it will be the beginning address of the struct
所以对结构本身的内存引用将是结构的起始地址
And then I'll use appropriate offsets to get to the different fields
然后我将使用适当的偏移来得到不同的字段
So here's an example of some code
这是一些代码的例子
Imagine I have a struct pointer to one of these structures
加入，我有一个指向这里其中一个结构的结构指针
And I have an index and what I want to do is get to the...uh...that
我有一个索引，我想要做的就是得到
appropriate part of array a within this struct
此结构中数组 a 的相应元素
Well array a is right at the beginning of the structure
好吧，数组 a 正好在结构的开头
So I can treat this just like I would (treat) any array reference
所以我可以像对待任何数组引用一样来对待它
uh...scaling idx by 4 and adding it to the base to get the appropriate element
即将 idx 乘上 4，并将其加到基地址上以获得相应的元素
So I don't really have to do anything special for this one
所以对这个例子，我真的不需要做任何特别的事情
Let's look at some other code that you'll typically see. Actually this example is pretty involved.
让我们看一下你通常会碰到的其他代码。实际上这个例子非常复杂
So I'm actually doing a whole bunch of stuff here with this one struct
实际上我在这里用一个结构做了很多东西
First of all I'm trying to retrieve element i from the structure
首先，我正在尝试从结构中取得元素 i
Then I'm using that to index into array a
然后我用它来索引数组 a
And and insert a value into there
然后在那里插入一个值
And then I'm updating this pointer to point to the next
然后我将更新此指针来指向下一个（结构）
uh...I'm...if this were a linked list what I want to do is step to the next over the list
如果这是一个链表，我想要做的是到链表的下一个节点去
So I need to retrieve the next field from here
所以我需要从这里得到下一个字段
And so these struc so I'm actually making three references to this structure
所以，实际上，在这么一个小小的函数里，我是对这个结构进行了三次引用
in this one rather small function. So let's try and figure it all out
让我们试着把它弄清楚吧
So first of all I have to retrieve element i from it
首先，我必须从中得到元素 i
And here you see that we know that element i is that offset 16
在这里你看到我们知道元素 i 的偏移是 16
And so if...and here's where you see that displacement field being used in the memory reference
你可以在此处看到位移字段在内存引用中被使用
Exactly for this purpose I want to take r, but add 16 to it to get a memory address that I can use for i
正是出于这个目的，我想拿 r，但给它加上16来得到一个可以获取 i 的内存地址
And you see it actually uses movq
你看它实际上使用 movq 指令
Because i itself is an int
因为 i 本身就是一个整数
But I'm going to use it as an array index in which case I have to scale it
但我将把它用作数组索引，这种情况下我必须伸缩它
I have to do a just arithmetic using 8 byte quantities
我必须使用8字节的数进行合适的算术运算
So this actually retrieves the four byte value and does a sign extension on it
所以这实际上拿到了四个字节的值并在其上做了一个符号扩展
And now what I want to do is store a val at element i
而现在我想做的是在元素 i 这里存储 val
And so here you'll see that it's using %rax, (%rax) is the value of just computed for i, scaling by 4
所以在这里你会看到它正在使用 %rax，%rax是我们刚刚计算的 i 的值，乘上 4
and using the starting address of the r which happens to be the starting address of a as well and doing a store
然后使用 r 的起始地址,这个地址恰好也是 a 的起始地址,并进行存储
So that's sort of an array operation there
所以这是那种数组操作
And then the next part is I'm going to offset 24 which is the position of next
然后下一部分我是要加上 24字节的偏移，这样就了得到 next 的位置
Read from that location and store that in %rdi which is a r
从该位置读取值并将其存储在 %rdi 即 r 中
So this is the operation r gets r->next
所以这是 r = r->next 操作
And then the loop is I'm testing until r is null. So that's going on here
然后一直循环下去，直到 r 为空。所以这就是这里的代码所做的事
So you see that those three references to the struct were implemented using three instructions here
所以你看到对结构的三次引用是使用这里的三个指令实现的
So it's a very direct mapping between the code here and the x86 instructions
所以这里的代码和 x86 指令之间有非常直接的对应
And part of the x86 instructions because this kind of stuff is so commonplace in programs
和一部分 x86 指令有直接对应是因为这种东西在程序中是如此常见
They kind of made the instructions map very directly toward these operations
他们让指令非常直接地对应到这些操作上
And now you should probably see why all the bells and whistles are there for these address references
而现在你应该明白为什么有各种绚酷的指令于这些地址引用
Question
有问题请讲
[student speaking] What if i was three
[学生说] 如果 i 是3怎么办？
[professor speaking] I'm sorry
[老师说话] 对不起，请再说一遍
Oh a had three elements
哦，（数组） a 有三个元素
Yes it will access...
是的，它将访问...
Actually I think that's a typo, a is supposed to be four..
实际上我认为这里写错了，a（的大小）应该是 4
[student speaking] ....
[学生说话] .......
[老师说话] So if i is four, it would access itself, yeah, and it would mess things up
因此，如果i 是 4，它会访问自己，是的，然后它会搞砸事情的
Question this is a typo by the way it should be a[4]
有问题请讲，顺便说下，这里写错了，这里应该写成 a[4]
[student speaking] ....
[学生说话] .......
Yes, a null pointer is... a null is zero
是的，一个空指针是......一个 null 是零值
Um so that's sort of the easy version of structs. Now let's make them a little harder
这就是结构的简单版本。现在我们让它们变得复杂一点
One is for reasons that are a bit obscure
一个是出于有点让人费解的原因
The machine generally prefers that if you have a data type, an underlying data type of k bytes
如果你有一个 k 字节的数据类型，机器通常更喜欢
that the address that that starts at be a multiple of k
起始的地址是 k 的倍数
And so that introduces a property we call alignment
所以这引入了一个我们称之为对齐的属性
which...well actually when a structure gets allocated
实际上，当一个结构被分配（内存空间）时
well the the compiler will actually insert some blank unused bytes in the data structure
编译器实际上会在分配空间时，在数据结构中插入一些空白的不被使用的字节
in its allocation just so that it can maintain this alignment
这么做只是为了保持这种对齐
So for example here i is an int
例如，这里 i 是一个整数
And I want its address to be a multiple of four
我希望它的地址是四的倍数
I'll give you...a minute...why that's true
我会在一分钟后，告诉你为什么是这个样子
I just so trust me for a minute
请相信我，给我一分钟的时间
And so it will actually pad three unused bytes here
所以它实际上有三个不被使用的字节
Because the first byte is being used by c
因为 c 正在用第一个字节
And in general we'll see in the allocation we're going to make sure that
总的来说，我们将看到，在分配空间时，我们将确保这一点
the pointer to this data structure is itself a multiple of eight
即指向此数据结构的指针本身是八的倍数
And the reason for that is because there's a double here
原因是这里有一个双精度数
And it should reside on a boundary that its starting address should be a multiple of eight
它应该位于一个边界上，这样浮点数的起始地址是 8 的倍数
And you'll see as long as this is eight...a multiple of 8
你会看到，只要这是 8 的倍数，
and this offset here is a multiple of 8
同时这里的偏移 是8 的倍数
then this address will be a multiple of eight
那么这个地址将是 8 的倍数
That's an idea of alignment
这是一种对齐的想法
And so why is that true, well it's really a hardware issue that
那么为什么要这么做，好吧，这实际上是一个硬件问题
the memory system sort of...the actual hardware memory does not reference
即内存系统，实际的硬件内存一次不取一个字节
one byte at a time, it references—actually in most machines nowadays—about 64 bytes at a time
实际上现在的大多数机器，一次取大约64个字节
Or depending on various widths within the hardware
或者这取决于硬件中的各种宽度
And in general with if a particular piece of data across
一般来说，如果因为没有一个对齐的地址，一个特定的数据跨越了两个块之间的边界，
the boundaries between two blocks that are...because of a misaligned address,
那么这会让硬件甚至有可能操作系统来采取一些额外的步骤来处理
that will take extra steps by the hardware
and potentially even the operating system to deal with
So just for efficiency reason they say do this alignment, trust me
因此，只是出于效率原因，他们说：相信我，进行数据对齐吧
In x86 machines if you have unaligned data it will execute just fine
在 x86 机器中，如果你有未对齐的数据，机器会正常执行（指令）的
It just might run a little bit more slowly
只是有可能会更慢一点
On some other machines if you try to do an unwind access it will actually cause a memory fault
在其他一些机器上，如果你尝试进行访问未对齐的数据，实际上这会导致内存错误
Question! Yes, the C compli...
有问题请讲！是的，C 编译器......
The question was how could you force it to generate unaligned data
问题是你怎么能强制它生成未对齐的数据
I don't know if you could
我不知道你能不能
And we'll talk about ways you can sort of be more clever in how you do your allocation to avoid wasting space
我们将讨论更灵活的分配方式以避免浪费空间
So in general then we have...
所以总的来说我们有......
We're mostly looking here at data types that are either 1, 2 or 4, 8 bytes long
我们主要关注的是1, 2 或 4, 8 字节大小的数据类型
There are some 16 byte data types
还有一些16 字节大小的数据类型
But we won't be looking at those
但我们不会关注那些
And in general with the address then you can tell the alignment of an address by how many zeros
通常，你可以通过有多少个零来判断地址的对齐方式
—if it's a power of 2 alignment—how many zeros are at the end of a bit level representation of that address
如果它是2的幂对齐的话，通过在该地址的位级表示的末尾有多少个零来判断
And so as we showed in general the C compiler when it's creating the layout for a structure a struct
如我们之前所展示的，在创建结构的布局时，C编译器通常会
will put in padding bytes in there to make the alignment work
将在其中放入填充字节以让数据对齐
Uh the other thing it will do is if it need be
它会做的另一件事，如果需要的话，是
it will add bytes to the end to make sure that the overall size of the data structure meets
它将在末尾添加字节以确保数据结构的总体大小满足
whatever underlying alignment requirement there is. This one, because it contains a double,
下层有的对齐要求，无论是什么。这个例子里，因为它包含一个双精度
the overall data structure has to be aligned on an 8 byte boundary
整个数据结构必须在 8 字节边界上对齐
And the reasoning for that is imagine I had an array of structs, of these structs in particular
而对此的思路是，假设有一个结构数组，特别是这些结构的一个数组
then if I can assume that if I can ensure that this array is a multiple...address is a multiple of eight
那么，如果我可以确保地址是 8 的倍数，
then you can see that each successive element of this array of these structs  is a multiple of eight
那么，你可以看到这个数组或这些结构体的每个连续元素（的地址）是 8 的倍数
And then within that struct I've ensured that each field that requires an alignment by eight
然后在该结构中，我已经确保每个需要按照8字节对齐的字段
is...uh...positioned with an offset that's a multiple of eight
已经按照 8 的倍数的偏移放置了
And so it all works out. But if you try to tinker with this by making this too short
所以所有的都对齐了。但如果你试图通过修补让它变得太短，
then you start getting misaligned references
那么你就开始得到错位（没有对齐）的引用了
And so one thing you'll see is for every struct the actual alignment requirement depends on
因此，你将看到的一件事是每个结构实际的对齐要求取决于
what's the sort of worst-case alignment the the maximum alignment of any element
什么是最坏情况的对齐，即任何元素的最大对齐要求
So this particular structure for example
所以，例如，这个特定的结构
contains a float v which has a size of four and so this would be an alignment of four
包含一个大小为 4 的浮点数 v，因此这将是四字节对齐
And you'll see in the code
你会在代码中看到
in general when it has to...this...all this address arithmetic
一般来说，这些我们看到的地址运算
we've seen gets used in various different ways to scale values, compute offsets and so forth to get the appropriate elements
被以各种不同的方式用来伸缩值、计算偏移量等等来得到相应的元素
So your question before is could I tell the compiler not to do alignment
所以你之前的问题是我可以让编译器不要做对齐
And the better way is to declare your fields
遥更好的方法是声明你的字段
in a way that minimizes the amount of wasted space
以最小化浪费空间量的方式
So for example here
例如这里
I wasted three bytes here and three bytes here to meet the alignment requirements
我在这里浪费了三个字节，三个字节是为了满足对齐要求
But if I just put i at the beginning and then c and d
但是，如果我只是把 i 放在开头，然后再是 c 和 d
I would have only wasted two bytes (in) total
总共我只会浪费两个字节
And in general because all the alignment requirements are powers of two
通常因，为所有对齐要求都是2的幂
the sort of greedy algorithm works it says if I just take put the biggest stuff at the beginning
如果我只是把最大的东西放在开头，再依次放更小的元素，那种贪心的算法是有效的
and then successfully smaller elements
I will be able to minimize any wasted space
我将能够最大限度地减少任何浪费的空间
And that's a general property but
这是一般的性质。但是，
this is a case where you is the writer of C code have that effect
这是你，作为C代码的作者，带来这种效果的情况
The compiler will not do this for you automatically
编译器不会自动替你这么做
Question
有问题请讲！......什么？
Oh but remember an array...I don't care about the array, I care about the elements of the array
哦，但记住我不关心数组，我关心的是数组的元素
Because this is only done at the lowest level where I'm accessing either a single int, a single double or a pointer
因为这只是最低的级别进行的，即我访问单个整数、单个双精度数或指针这个最低级别
And not all the rest of this stuff. Remember I never read an entire array from memory
而不是所有其它的东西。记住，我从来没有从内存中读取整个数组
So alignment only refers down to the most primitive types not the aggregate types
因此，对齐仅指最原始的数据类型而言，不包括聚合数据类型
If this is confusing the book covers this fairly carefully
如果这令人困惑，课本已经非常仔细地介绍这点了
So let me just finish up with a little glimpse of floating point
好了，让我们稍微了解浮点数来结束本堂课
Uh...floating point is a complicated history in x86, back in the really ancient days
浮点数在 x86 里有复杂的历史。在回到很古老的时候，那时
there was a chip that went with the 8086 processor called the 8087
8086 处理器上有一块称为 8087 的芯片
And uh...the time it was a masterpiece of engineering to be able to complete all the hardware necessary to implement
当时，能够完成所有所需的硬件以在单个芯片上实现完整的 IEEE 浮点数是工程上的杰作
full IEEE floating point on a single chip
And it was the first one of its type
而它是它这个类型芯片的第一块
In fact it was a sort of co-developed with the IEEE floating point standard itself
事实上，它是与 IEEE 浮点标准本身共同开发的
But the programming model for it is horrendously awful and ugly
但它的编程模型非常糟糕和丑陋
I used to....in older editions of the book, there were
在这本书的旧版本中
it was in the first edition，it was in a web aside in the second edition
在第一版里有，第二版里是放在网页旁注(web aside)里
And now it's been expunged completely because it's so awful
而现在它已被彻底清除，因为它太糟糕了
But more recently in the world of x86
但最近在 x86 的世界里
they realized that to support things like video and all the stuff people actually do with their machines
他们意识到要支持视频以及人们用电脑真正要做的所有事情
they needed some more horsepower in numeric processing
他们在数值处理方面需要更多的马力
They implemented a class of instructions called SSE
他们实现了一类名为 SSE 的指令
which stands for SIMD something SIMD execution
这代表SIMD什么什么执行
Anyways and I'll show you in a minute what that means
无论如何，我会在一分钟内告诉你那意味着什么
And that's now in the more recent versions of x86
现在，在 x86 的最近的版本里，
has been juiced up to something called AVX
已经被提炼成称为 AVX 的东西
which....but the shark machines support this version of what's called SSE. So let me just give you a feeling for that
但是鲨鱼机器（CMU的课程实验机器）支持这个所谓的SSE版本。那么让我给你一个感觉
And in particularly the shark machine support what's called SSE version 3
特别是鲨鱼机器支持所谓的 SSE 版本3
And what it is that...there are 16 special registers
有16 个特殊的寄存器 ，完全不同于我们之前讨论过的寄存器
distinct from the other registries we've talked about before
Each of which has 16 bytes
每个寄存器都有16个字节
And then there's operations that can operate on those and treat them in different ways
然后就是可以对它们进行操作、并以不同方式对待它们的指令
So one is to treat this...such an a register as an array of 16 chars
其中一个指令是这样的，将这样一个寄存器视为16个字符
or as eight shorts or four ints or...and also to support uh...double floating-point arithmetic
或者作为8个短整型数据或四个整数或......并且还支持双精度浮点运算
So this stuff was certainly going on
所以这样的东西肯定在继续下去
And somebody had the observation that said well:
有人曾经作出过很好的评论
I could just then sort of subset all this and implement the floating-point operations
我可以对所有这些进行子集化，然后实现浮点数运算
directly using this SSE stuff and skip the old x87 stuff
直接使用这个 SSE 的东西，跳过旧的 x87 东西
And so that's the way floating point is now generated on say the shark machines and most recent machines
所以这就是在鲨鱼机器和最新机器上处理浮点数的方式
This is again an example of where the world is more complicated than it should have to be
这又是一个现实比它本来更复杂的例子
So for example there is an instruction that says addss
例如，有一条写成 addss 的指令
So add a single scalar is what that notation...add a single precision scalar...
那么（这条指令）是指对单精度标量做加法运算
add a scaler single-precision
And it looks a little like the add instructions...the addq instructions you've seen that
它看起来有点像你见过的 addq 指令
It increments...it adds the source to the destination
它将源的值加到目的的值上
There's ways I can do for adds all at the same time
有方法可以让我同时进行加法运算
Using this is what they call SIMD execution
即使用他们所谓的 SIMD （指令）执行
which stands for single instruction multiple data
这是 single instruction multiple data（单指令多数据）的缩写
One instruction the addps stands for pact
单个指令 addps，p是指 pack（一组），
will do...will perform...that one instruction will do add with four different numbers
就能同时对四个不同的数进行加法运算
And similarly you can do it with double precision you can do one of them you can do pack
类似的，你可以用来操作双精度浮点数，你可以一个一个来，你也可以一组同时来
And so actually the underlying...and we'll see this when we look at code optimization
当我们学代码优化那一章时，我们会看到这一点即
If you write code to make use of these instructions you can really boost the performance of the computer
如果你利用这些指令来写代码，你可以大大提高计算机的性能
But this just gives you a flavor for what floating-point code looks like
不过这里只是给你看看浮点数代码的样子
And the rules are pretty simple that just as we saw before that
就像我们之前看到的那样，规则非常简单，即
that arguments get passed in in registers
参数传入寄存器中
Well, float-point arguments get passed in these xmm registers
好吧，浮点数参数传入这些 XMM 寄存器里
%xmm0 you don't have to memorize %rdi, %rsi, %rdx
%xmm0......你不需要像 %rdi, %rsi, %rdx 这样去记
They are %xmm zero one two it's all very logical
这些寄存器是按照 %xmm0, %xmm1, %xmm2...这样的方式命名，都非常符合逻辑
And the return value is in %xmm0
而返回值是放在 %xmm0 里
And all the registers are called caller-saved there's no callee-saved
并且所有寄存器都被是调用者保存，没有被调用者保存的寄存器
So something like adding two floating point numbers will just look like a single floating point addition instruction
所以同时对两个浮点数进行加法运算的指令，就像对一个浮点进行加法运算的指令一样
Same with double
双精度浮点数据也是如此
And if you mix together code that has a pointer and a floating point operator,
如果你将代码混在一起，既有指针的运算符，也有浮点数的运算符
the pointer will be passed in a regular register %rdi
指针将传到常规寄存器 %rdi 中
and this double will be passed in %xmm0
而这个双精度浮点数将传入 %xmm0 中
So it's sort of...as it goes through the argument list you sort of in the particular order
所以它有点像...在处理参数列表时，是按照特定顺序来的
If it's an integer or a pointer, it's in one of the r registers
如果是整数或指针，则位于 r 开头的其中一个寄存器
And if it's a floating point value it's in one of the xmm registers and potentially interleaved
如果它是一个浮点数，它在一个 XMM 寄存器中，并且可能是交错的
Almost done
课快讲完了
And so this is a code that does this particular operation
所以这是一段进行这个特定操作的代码
And it's interesting because it's returning a...
这段代码有趣是因为它返回了一个......
It's doing memory referencing so...
是因为它正在做内存引用，这样......
Again there's instructions that will read from memory and copy into an XMM register
同样，有指令将从内存中读取并复制到一个 XMM 寄存器中
You can add registers you can make a copy of from one xmm register to another and you can store results
你可以对一个寄存器进行加法运算，你可以从一个 XMM 寄存器复制到另一个 XMM 寄存器里，你还可以存储结果
So this code looks a lot like what you do in integer arithmetic except it's using xmm and special floating-point instructions
因此，除了使用 XMM 寄存器和特殊浮点指令、而不是你见过的那些（寄存器和指令）之外，这段代码看起来很像整数运算
rather than the ones you've seen before
So the basic idea of it is fairly simple
所以它的基本思想非常简单
It gets way more complicated because there are lots of instructions
它会变得复杂很多是因为有很多很多的指令
Double float but on and on and on there's a special instruction to do square root and all this stuff
不单单是双精度浮点数，还有其它各种形式的（比如单精度、标量、矢量等），都有一个特殊的指令来算包括平方根在内的所有东西
And the comparison stuff is really nasty and messy and hard to understand
（浮点）比较的东西（操作）真的很讨厌，很乱，很难理解
And then uh you'll see various tricks to use constant values to
然后你会看到使用常数的各种技巧
So that's covered in the book, we're not going to really talk about it much in this course
课本已经包含这些内容了，我们将不会在课堂里中真正谈论太多
But the underlying...the the basic principle of float-point are fairly straightforward
但是，浮点（体系）的基本原理是相当简单的
Okay, that'll do us for today
好了，今天的课到此结束